<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter farther and more fully evidencing the Kings stedfastnesse in the Protestant religion, written by Mounsier de l'Angle minister of the Protestant church at Roven in France to a friend of his in London,</title>
            <author>L'Angle, Samuel de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1027_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202710</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862906</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862906</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168872</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168872)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1027[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter farther and more fully evidencing the Kings stedfastnesse in the Protestant religion, written by Mounsier de l'Angle minister of the Protestant church at Roven in France to a friend of his in London,</title>
                  <author>L'Angle, Samuel de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A.W. for Joshua Kirton at the Queens Arms in St. Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A variant has replaced the imprint word "Queens" with "Kings".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 1".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168872:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER Farther and more fully Evidencing the Kings ſtedfaſtneſſe in THE Proteſtant Religion, Written by <hi>Mounſier de l'Angle</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Proteſtant Church at <hi>Roven</hi> in <hi>FRANCE</hi> to a Friend of his in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.W.</hi> for <hi>Joſhua Kirton</hi> at the Queens Arms in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168872:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168872:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He reverend Author judgeing it fit, and to good purpoſe to publiſh this Letter of his in <hi>France,</hi> both for the comforts and undeceiving of the Proteſtants of that Nation, in that great ſcandal caſt on the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as inclining to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which ſcandal though it be now fully cleared, and made evident as our Author ſaith, that it came from Hell, ſo that it might ſeem to no purpoſe to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh any farther vindication of his Majeſty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Yet the ſame reaſons mentioned before for publiſhing of the original, together with the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of the Author, who is one of the ancienteſt Preachers in <hi>France,</hi> and the fulneſs of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein are many things not commonly known, were strong inducements for publiſhing this tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
<pb facs="tcp:168872:3"/>whereby all true Engliſh men and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants may alſo receive much comfort, and all prejudice removed from their hearts, who in the leaſt doubt of the ſincerity of the King, concerning the Religion he profeſſeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:168872:3"/>
            <head>A Letter of <hi>M.</hi> de <hi>l'Angle,</hi> Divine, to a friend concerning the Religion of the Serene King of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ogether with all known good men, I prayſed God, when I underſtood the proceedings in <hi>Engl.</hi> tended to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhment of your King; and again, I glorify'd him, for the evidence appears that he will have compaſſion on that miſerable Kingdom, long known to me, and whereas you well know I did for ſome years preach the Goſpel to a people that lov'd me, and in whom I obſerv'd much of piety. 'Tis true, the people, whereof the ſtate at preſent is compos'd, make up a various co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured garment, which God in his Law allows not of; And this prodigious compound of Frogs and Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168872:4"/>that is, the Sectaries, which cover allmoſt all <hi>England,</hi> made me feare the wrath of God would not long forbear this deſolate Nation.</p>
            <p>But God, who is rich in mercy, who for the ſake of ten righteous, would have pardoned <hi>Sodom,</hi> hath yet more inclination to pardon his Hieruſalem, for the pious multitude in the mid'ſt of it, who ſincerely love God, and by whom his holy name is called on, eſpecially I had a confidence that firſt or laſt the Presbyterians, thoſe who at preſent make the ſtrongeſt party in great <hi>Britain,</hi> would by examples of loyalty, when God ſhould afford them opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, clear themſelves of the infamy they are blaſted wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, for being complices in the death of King Charles of bleſſed and glorious memory. And that to thoſe of our Religion would be reſtored the glory. Cardinal <hi>Oſſat</hi> in one of his Epiſtles ingeniouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth our due, that is, never to have attempted the life of our Soveraignes, how cruel ſo ever they have been to us; and notwithſtanding the maſſacres upon thoſe of our Religion by their orders, theſe or ſuch like are the Cardinals own words.</p>
            <p>Whereupon Sir, I ſhall tell you that diſcourſing ſome dayes ſince with a perſon of Judgement, and one fearing God, of the ſtate of your affairs, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of thoſe affairs in this conjuncture ſo croſs for the King, that ſeem to obſtruct his re-eſtabliſhment, we concluded that amongſt others, two grand Obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles concurr'd to hinder it, which would infallibly ſucceed, could they be taken away.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the apprehenſion that the Presbyterians, who only are capable to bring this about, in behalf of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168872:4"/>the Church and State, may have, that the King di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtes them, holding them guilty of the parricide of the King his Father, as ſome have endeavoured to perſwade him; ſome out of malice to foment an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcilible miſunderſtanding betwixt the King and his beſt Subjects, and ſo to order it, that they may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hereafter have confidence in each other. Others out of unadviſedneſs, being miſinform'd in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of that ſaid ſtory, as the late <hi>Salmaſius</hi> in his Apologie for the King of <hi>England,</hi> where this great perſon exaſperates himſelf with a falſe generoſity, when he declares he was not born for compliance, whereof no man ever ſuſpected him, and that he ſpares neither brother, nor beſt friend, where he finds them deviated from their duty.</p>
            <p>The other obſtacle we judged to withſtand the Kings re-eſtabliſhment, is a perſwaſion that the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Proteſtant Religion, and the King of <hi>England</hi> have ſowed amongſt many, that the King is not of the Religion he profeſſeth, but that he concurs with <hi>Rome,</hi> wherewith he hath private engagements, in a word, that he is a Papiſt.</p>
            <p>To take away the firſt obſtacle, I ſhew'd this good man a letter I ſometime wrote to <hi>Salmaſlus,</hi> of whom I ſpake concerning his Apologie, which he did me the honour to ſend me. In this letter where I ſhew'd him that as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid to <hi>Reuben</hi> his firſt-born,<note place="margin">Gen 49.</note> he was unſtable as water, and ſhould not excel; I have ſo evidently clear'd the Presbyterians of the injury he did them, and with reaſons ſo conſiderable, that the perſon to whom I communicated them, thought it fit the letter ſhould be publiſhed; whereto I willingly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168872:5"/>conſented, judging the Letter would come forth to purpoſe, and in ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>But the poſture wherein at preſent I view them, and the affection they teſtifie to their Prince, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies them above all the reaſons I alleadg'd, and if their great and glorious deſigne ſucceeds, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches in all parts of the Wrold evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray, like <hi>Moſes</hi> lifting up their hands, till God makes this happy day ſhine from above; their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe will appear ſo manifeſt, that Calumny it ſelf will not dare to attempt it. For what man of reaſon ſees not that <hi>if their hearts condemn'd them,</hi> and that they were conſcious of this crying ſin, they would not be cautious of procuring the Kings return, ſince they muſt needs have cauſe to fear he ſhould retain an immortal reſentment; and though for a time find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their party, as the ſons of <hi>Zerviah, too ſtrong and potent for him,</hi> he diſſembles the indignation conceiv'd in his heart, they muſt alwaies think he would make them feel the effects when time ſhould favour him.</p>
            <p>And this argument is confirmed by the example of the Sectaries, who fearing their hands ſhould be found ſtain'd with the blood that cries ſo loud, apprehend the Kings re-eſtabliſhment as a ſad day for them; when this Prince may treat them in ſuch termes, as he, of whom the Scripture tells us, did thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from their obedience, and that in his juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments: he ſaith not, <hi>Bring me hither theſe my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> which would not that I ſhould <hi>raign over them;</hi> Though to deale ingeniouſly, I believe their fear will be their only puniſhment, and I am confident he is a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168872:5"/>Prince, who will do by his ſubjects as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did by his bretheren, and as he had reſpect to the deſires of his dying father <hi>Jacob, to pardon his bretheren,</hi> and not regard the evil they had done him, that ſo the King by the example of the ſonne of God, by whom he ſhall raigne, God aſſiſting, may <hi>make grace abound where ſinne abounds,</hi> and in obſervance of the King his Fathers ſage and Chriſtian advice brought him by ſome that attended at his death, which were to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don his people, and with a general Oblivion prevent their cries and lamentations.</p>
            <p>But the other Obſtacle ſtands yet, and is of more importance: that is, the Calumny taken upon truſt from hand to hand, that the King is of the <hi>Roman</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and will ſoon make it appear, when he gets the raines of the Realme in his hands, Sir, Upon this point I muſt tell you, that ſome yeares ſince this ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſprung from Hell, I have made it my work to know the truth, have us'd all ſorts of means to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what his heart was as towards God; and if he were ſuch as he was repreſented to me. For this cauſe I followed him with a vigilant eye all the time he ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>France</hi> after the battel he loſt againſt <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and again after he retired to <hi>Bruxells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that which drew me to this curioſity, was not the tenents of thoſe, who hold, that if the King prove not of the Proteſtant Religion, we are not onely to abandon his Intereſts, but with our power to oppoſe his return to the Crown; for I have not ſo learned <hi>Chriſt;</hi> nor can I be perſwaded that becauſe a man is not of our opinion in matter of Religion, it is a ſufficient title to deprive him of his Right: and I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168872:6"/>leave thoſe deformed opinions that overturn the foundations of States, and render Chhriſtian Religion incompatable with all the Polices of the Univerſe, to ſuch extravagant brains as hold the earth belongs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to the Saints, ſuch as they take themſelves to be, and that the portion which every one, who is not of the fraternity of theſe fanatick ſpirits, enjoys, is detain'd by injuſtice, and abſolute uſurpation. And by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence I cannot imagine the people of <hi>England</hi> were well principalled, to caſt their naturall Prince out of his Kingdom, under colour that he was of a religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theirs. For, I know amongſt the people of God there was never any ſuch practice. And, that under all the legall diſpenſation ſince the ſtate of the <hi>Jewes</hi> was devolv'd into the hands of Kings, the people never roſe againſt their Prince for his Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, but when oblig'd by expreſſe command from God.<note place="margin">As that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Jehu.</hi>
               </note> And ſince <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> came upon earth, the Chriſtians that firſt embrac'd his Doctrine, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver eſteem'd Idolatry, wherewith their <hi>Soveraigns</hi> were infected, ſufficient to diſcharge them from their obedience. The example of <hi>Julian</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate is in this deciſive, who revolting from Chriſtianiſme, and becoming an Apoſtate, and plunng'd in Pagan Idolatries, and by this means had return'd the Empire, which by a ſingular providence of God was fallen into the hands of Chriſtians, to the enemies of Chriſt an Religion, yet receiv'd ſtill homage from the Chriſtians of thoſe times, who bore their yoke with humility, becauſe 'twas God that laid it on them.</p>
            <p>And it clearly appear'd this ſubmiſſion of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168872:6"/>Church was acceptable to God, by his timely relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them from the perſecution of this powerfull and malicious enemy: for this change was but like a ſtorm that ſoon is over, and as a cloud, as an Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent calls it, which for a time ecclipſ'd the glory of the Chriſtian Church, but by the good providence of God was diſperſed in the turning of a hand, and the Empire reſtor'd to Chriſtian Princes, who ſet the Church in her luſter again.</p>
            <p>'Tis true that in our age that unfortunate faction call'd the League, ſtirred up by that ſpirit well known to all, inſolently publiſh'd that pernicious hereſy, that a Prince no ſooner with <hi>Rome,</hi> but he loſes his Rights to his Crown; and that the greater part of <hi>France</hi> poyſon'd with this pernicious beleif, uſ'd their utmoſt endeavours to have hinder'd <hi>Henry</hi> the great from aſcending the Throne, which he and his Poſterity have ſince ſo gloriouſly enjoy'd. But this doctrine went againſt the haire with all the good people of thoſe times, both of the one and the other Religion, and numbers of honeſt men ſet their tongues, their pens, and their ſwords, to work to maintain the Juſtice of that glorious Monarch, and beat back this dangerous Maxime down to Hell, where doubtleſſe 'twas firſt contriv'd.</p>
            <p>'Twas not then, Sir, for that I had the leaſt thought the Re-eſtabliſhment of the King of <hi>England</hi> in his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall inheritance ought to depend on his Religion, and that if I found he were imbu'd with the errours of the Roman Church, I ſhould have judg'd him incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of that high dignity; but for ſatiſfaction of my ſelf and all good people, to the end, that if according to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168872:7"/>the forejudgment I had allready in favour of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which he deriv'd by tradition from his father of bleſſed memory, to the conſtant profeſſion whereof he exhorted him at his death, I found him according to my hopes, my joy might be accompliſht, and I might ſpread the rumour every way, where I thought the welcom news might conduce to the procuring Juſtice for the beſt cauſe on earth, and that if amongſt his ſubjects that differ in this poynt from the common ſenſe of our Churches, which allmoſt unanimouſly will have us give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> what belongs to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to <hi>Caeſar</hi> I ſay, as to <hi>Caeſar</hi> only, and not for that he is a Proteſtant <hi>Caeſar,</hi> they may learn that their King is doubly the Annoynted of the Lord, and perſectly of the quality, they wiſh him, and ſo there is nothing why they ſhould not joyn with all other good ſubjects in the deſigne they appear to have of rein-throning him: ſince not only, there is no reaſon to oppoſe it, but more, there is not any pretence for it with the leaſt colour of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>To proceed, I learn for certain, he adher'd in his heart to the Proteſtant Religion, for as much as man can judge of the profundity of that part: I had it from ſuch as have the honour to be near his perſon. I am aſſur'd of it by the teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Long</hi> who had a ſhare in the weighty affayres of the late <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, and of this likewiſe, and who was one of thoſe attended him in his voyage to <hi>Scotland:</hi> A gentleman of an Excellent ſpirit, not eaſily to be tax'd with any thing, but a perſon of great integrity, and who for thoſe many yeares he liv'd amongſt us was an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding help to our Church, by his conſtant frequenting
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168872:7"/>of Sermons, and all acts of Piety can be required of a man fearing God; and who for my particular highly oblig'd me, not thinking me unworthy of his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, nor the honour of his friendſhip. He in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy of our moſt intimate communications, hath a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times proteſted to me, that the King of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> in the bottom of his heart is of our Religion, and was aſſur'd the Church of God would ackowledge him, and the time ſhould come ſhe would hold him her moſt precious Ornament. 'Tis true, this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath his ſoul tranſfixt with the love of his King, but I am certain he hath a greater love to Truth, and would not affirm a falſhood ſo conſtantly &amp; with ſuch affeveration for all the Crowns on earth.</p>
            <p>I know likewiſe what he appear'd in this Town, which was one of his firſt retreats after his defeat at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and that all his diſcourſe with thoſe who had the honour to converſe with him, came from a heart ſanctifi'd with the truth of the Goſpel. He ſpoke the very Language of <hi>Canaan,</hi> he reprov'd ſuch as mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur'd, with <hi>David</hi> he conceal'd his deplorable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Becauſe 'twas God that did it.</hi> To ſome pious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, friends of mine he ſhew'd divers excellent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for his divine entertainments, accommodated to the preſent eſtate he was reduc'd to. All his diſcourſes were ſeaſon'd with nothing but faith, humility, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and abſolute reſignation to the will of God, who thrones, and dethrones Kings, as it pleaſes him, <hi>who girds them with the ſword;</hi> but when he pleaſes to manifeſt his judgements, cryes over their Crowne, <hi>Subverſion, Subverſion.</hi> But by theſe diſcourſes it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that he gather'd great hopes of unexpected re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168872:8"/>in the mercies of God; who, when he will, can raiſe with as great celerity as throw down, and when he pleaſes changes <hi>our Deſarts</hi> into <hi>Carmel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, all that came near him, obſerv'd a great ſoul not to be dejected by affliction, who with a ſpirit perfectly noble &amp; Chriſtian fuſtain'd himſelf in God, to whom he reſign'd his perſon and all his intereſts, and, who with the ſame devotion kiſs'd the hand of God that came to take off his Crown with his Fathers head, as hereafter he will kiſſe it again when he ſhall pleaſe to reſtore it. Now Sir, 'tis not unknown to you, that none but the true Religion gives this temper, and none but the pure Gold ſtands the tryal of this teſte. And as in <hi>Daniel,</hi> he who walked in the midſt of the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace was known by his gate to be the ſonne of God; certainly he hath little ſkill in men that could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his carriage in theſe times of tryal to be the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of a true child of God, and ſay of him, <hi>Thou art a Galilean, for thy language ſhews it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afterwards I am aſſur'd, he teſtified great affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſuch Paſtors as had the honour to ſalute him in <hi>France,</hi> and by the Lady <hi>Iſabella,</hi> daughter to the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> when ſhe took her leave of him at <hi>Amiens,</hi> he ſent to me to remember him in my prayers, which muſt not be attributed to any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe I have had with this Prince; for I proteſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God I never had any, that I never ſaw, nor ſpake to him, and that I have no engagement with him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther real, nor verbal, nor of perſonal hope, and though I wiſh him all happeneſſe imaginable, I nevertheleſſe expect not any thing from him, But I believe ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental occaſion brought may name to his eare, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168872:8"/>hearing I was Paſtor of a populous Church, he was pleaſed to teſtifie by this obliging requeſt, he was of the ſame Communion with me.</p>
            <p>Again, I know him to be as you and I wiſh him out of the atteſts of his own Miniſters, Doctor <hi>Coſins</hi> amongſt the reſt, a perſon venerable both for Doctrine and Piety. And by the teſtimony of the <hi>Mesſieurs Breuins</hi> and <hi>Durel,</hi> both eminent Paſtours, really na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſubjects of the King of <hi>England,</hi> and who are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd with a ſhare in his favours. But I have ſo thorough a knowledge of them, and ſo well know the candour and love they bear the Truth, which they teach with ſuch happy ſucceſſe; one with the Prince of <hi>Turenne,</hi> the other with the Duke <hi>De la Force,</hi> that I admire with as great acquieſcence as a thing I had ſeen with my eyes, or touch'd with my hands, what they have oftentimes affirm'd to me, that the King of <hi>England</hi> is a Proteſtant, and of the beſt ſort, and that 'tis not meerly ſecular intereſts engage him on this party; but that he is ſo at the heart, and that he makes the Religion he profeſſes his Treaſure; of which they could not well be ignorant, having attentively obſerved his wayes and carriage from his Infancy.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe 'twill not be amiſſe to tell you, that of theſe two Gentlemen, <hi>Breuins</hi> and <hi>Durel,</hi> the King hath choſen the firſt for one of his Chaplains, that is his Miniſters in ordinary, by reaſon this choyce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes the proof, we endeavour to make of the Kings Religion: and, ſince he made election of one of the moſt zealous Profeſſours of the Proteſtant Religion, moſt capable to defend it, and ſhew the beauty of it for one of the Directors of his conſcience, 'tis an evident
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168872:9"/>teſtimony, he conſents with him in Religion, and will perſevere under his example and conduct.</p>
            <p>Which is likewiſe confirm'd by what I learn from all parts that he frequented o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Sermons at <hi>Rochelie</hi> and other parts of <hi>France,</hi> but particularly at this Town, where, with the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended him, without ſitting down he heard the Sermon of <hi>Mounſieur Janſſe</hi> my <hi>Colleague,</hi> and told one to whom he diſcovered himſelf, he had received great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed fication. And 'tis obſervable he came <hi>incognito</hi> to theſe Aſſemblies, and by conſequence for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then Devotion. If he had been known to every one, and had come in a publick way, out of the violent inclination of his enemies to a ſiniſter interpretation of this unfortunate Princes actions, they would have ſaid this was but a deſigne, and he did it to regain credit with his people; but ſince he was concealed, 'tis an aſſured teſtimony, he had no other aime than his particular benefit.</p>
            <p>Then the teſtimony of a Noble-man of note of the reformed Religion, that is the Count of <hi>Suze</hi> is very conſiderable to me, I ſaw him lately, and intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him ſeriouſly to tell me what he thought of the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Religion, I addreſs'd my ſelf to him for ſatisfaction herein, becauſe he was diverſe years at <hi>Bruxels</hi> with Monſieur the Prince, whoſe cauſe he had eſpous'd, and I knew moreover that the King of <hi>England</hi> was often with the Prince, and that there was a great familiarity betwixt them: The anſwer he made me was, but what I knew before, that the King of <hi>England</hi> while he was at <hi>Bruxels</hi> made high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our Religion, and that every Sunday he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168872:9"/>diligently was very carefull to celebrate the duties thereof in his lodgings, that to his knowledge his pulſe had been often felt, but he had made them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, he was not that way to be taken, and that he knew in whom he believed, and that his conſcience was not like lands unknown, at the mercy of the firſt comer. I acknowledge I make great account of this teſtimony, becauſe I know, he that gave it is a perſon of integrity, that he was ever preſent at the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements of theſe two great Princes, and in fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar converſations one may beſt diſcover a man, and know his waies. I know again with what indignation he receiv'd the Earle of <hi>Briſtol</hi> not long after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt. This Lord is a perſon of a great wit and high courage, but I leave it to himſelf to decide, if his conſcience hath walk'd in as gracefull a poſture, as the other two faculties, &amp; whether he finde it very tender in matters of Religion, I will think the beſt I may, and will not deſpair, but God may recal him, and grant him mercy; but I ſhould make a very ſiniſter Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if he were ſuch as he is character'd, for I have been told he is a man can change Religion as his clothes, not alwaies for the better, but the more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and convenient. Howſoever it is, I underſtood when he went hence, he addreſs'd himſelf to the King, after his uſual manner; but was much amaz'd when the King ſharply reprehended him for the ſcandal he had given, and gave him to underſtand he was not pleas'd to ſee him in his traine or family, ſince he was not a domeſtick of the Faith.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt forgotten one paſſage, that may aſſure you the King is ſenſible of this Article of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168872:10"/>Religion: and that he is not ſatisfied to <hi>believe</hi> to righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe <hi>in his heart,</hi> but he will have the world to know him for what he is, and that he will make <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> with the <hi>mouth to Salvation.</hi> You are not unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>la Milletiere,</hi> and the vanities of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſome yeares ſince, he had the boldneſſe to addreſſe one of his works to the King of <hi>England,</hi> wherein he diſcours'd with this Prince, as if there had been ſome great intelligence betwixt them, and as if he had been upon the point to revolt. But the King in indignation ſhew'd him the boldneſſe of his enterprize, the vanity of his hopes, and the impertinency of his reaſons, by a learned Treatiſe, he cauſed the Biſhop of <hi>London-Derry</hi> to compoſe, ſince tranſlated into <hi>French</hi> by one of ours.</p>
            <p>But Sir, after the Hiſtory of the Duke of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> I ſuppoſe there can remain no ſuſpicion of this Prince his Religion, it may be you know the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars as well as I, but truely I had the relation from the mouth of <hi>Monſieur Durel,</hi> who had it from the Governour of that little Prince.</p>
            <p>Here then I ſhall deliver what I know. The Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its had a deſigne to gain this Prince, for which purpoſe they ſound a way to have his Governour diſcharged. In purſuance whereof they made many aſſaults upon his Religion; they ſhew'd him a thouſand glorious hopes, they promiſed him the moſt important digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Church ſhould court him, aſſured him the Abbey of S. <hi>Dennis,</hi> the Archbiſhoprick of Rheims, and a Cardinal's cap. Briefly, theſe Gentlemen aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him he ſhould be ſo rich, he ſhould be able to reſtore the King his brother to his throne; but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168872:10"/>God aſſiſted this Prince in an extraordinary manner, and for the reproach of Chriſt, whom he took for his portion, he generouſly deſpis'd the <hi>treaſures</hi> of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Wherefore the Jeſuits carried him from place to place, as the Devil heretofore did our Lord to tempt him. Firſt to <hi>Pontoiſe,</hi> to a ſeminary of Jeſuites, where God gave him grace to withſtand ſtrong aſſaults, and by the ſtrength of his ſpirit, wherewith he ever aſſiſted this excellent Prince, who was not then above ten or twelve years of age, he remained victorious over his potent enemies, who now reſolv'd to bring him back to <hi>Paris,</hi> like <hi>Balaam</hi> that view'd the people of God on all ſides, to finde a prize for his charmes. But all this ſucceeded not, God every where protected this il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Infant, and God gave <hi>him that wiſdom from above, which the World cannot reſiſt;</hi> and God that permits not his to be tempted beyond their ſtrength, delivered him from temptation; for the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> underſtanding by the baniſhed Governour his brothers condition, ſent Marquiſs <hi>Ormond</hi> ſpeedily to his relief, who took him out of this dangerous way, by the Queens orders, who had the goodneſs to give way to the pleaſure of the King of <hi>England</hi> her ſon, and cauſed the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> to be remitted into the hands of the Marquiſs, who brought him back to the King, ſince which time he hath taken care for his education, and confirm'd him in the knowledge of the truth.</p>
            <p>Can there, Sir, be any thing more ſtrong and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to aſſure you the King is not only a Proteſtant by profeſſion, but that he profeſſes it with zeale, and that he beleeveth it the only way to ſalvation, ſince he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168872:11"/>was ſo tenderly touch'd when he was inform'd they would pervert his brother? And if the Religion of the King of <hi>England,</hi> had been no more then formality and countenance, the advantage he might have hop'd for in his brothers change might have brought him to conſent, ſince he might have pretended he had no hand in it, and have ſay'd, that being ſo many leagues diſtant, though Kings have long armes, he could not if he would ſtretch his ſo far to hinder his brothers fall.</p>
            <p>But we are to make anſwer to what his enemies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadg to prove the King of <hi>England</hi> of the Roman Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. 1. He was ſay they brought up with <hi>Charles</hi> the late King his father who gave him the firſt ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. 2. While he was at <hi>Paris</hi> he never came to a Sermon at <hi>Charenton.</hi> 3. He was ſeen in the Jeſuits houſe at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> At <hi>Paris</hi> and in other places, he was ſeen at <hi>Veſpers:</hi> 4. Then they make a great noiſe of this, that they of the Roman Church conceive great hopes in the reeſtabliſhment of this Prince, and that the Jeſuites and Monkes boaſt alowd they ſhall ſee the Popes authority flouriſh again, and Maſſe in more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in <hi>England</hi> then ever.</p>
            <p>But Sir I ſuppoſe you beleive that none but the weak and malicious will give credit to ſuch feeble reaſons, whereof ſome are altogether falſe and blaſphemous, others conclude nothing they undertake, and the reſt conclude contrary to the intention of the alleadgers.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe wicked Arguments which is the education of this Prince, in the Roman Religion by the late King his father is the moſt notorious calumny that ever was, which to falſhood couples Blaſphemy againſt the Powers,<note place="margin">St. Jude</note> and to falſhood, and blaſphemy, barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168872:11"/>and cruelty beyond example. For was there ever greater cruelty then not to be ſatisfy'd to have made King <hi>Charles</hi> the moſt unfortunate Prince the earth ever bore, having taken from him, by wayes unheard of, and ſuch as good people cannot think on without trembling and horrour, his Crown and life, but more to traduce him as the moſt deprav'd and artificiall hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite that ever liv'd. For they make him wear a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard all his life, to the houre of this death incluſively, which is notwithſtanding an hour when conſcience makes the man ſpeak truth in ſpight of himſelf, nor is there paint which melts not, when conſcience approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the fire of the Almighties wrath.</p>
            <p>All the world knows King <hi>Charles</hi> proteſted before, that were preſent when he renderd his ſoul to God, that he dyed of the Religion authoriz'd by the laws of <hi>England,</hi> nor is there any one dares deny a truth ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally atteſted. But ſuch ridiculous miſcreants there are, who have impudence to ſay this proteſtation was but a fiction, and ſuggeſted by the emiſſaries of the Pope. That 'twas done for policy, and that the Popes Indulgencies allow ſo far. But theſe impertinents tell not what was the politick end the <hi>Partizans</hi> of the Pope aym'd at, nor what advantage could redound to their religion, that the King of <hi>England</hi> even dying ſhould openly and firmly proteſt he was a proteſtant. But ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch an odde diſſimulation was maintaind for ſome reaſons to us unknown, who is it theſe people can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, that this Prince, who during his life, had ever gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven teſtimony of his ſingular piety, ſhould take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to damne himſelf by counterfeiting before God &amp; man, to favour the Intereſts of the Roman Religion.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168872:12"/>
            <p>I do not know that the Pope ever gave indulgence for ſinnes to be committed. Every one, nevertheleſſe, knowes the Hiſtory of the great <hi>Bulliſle Texel,</hi> the firſt that publiſh'd ſuch ſophiſticated ſtuff in <hi>Germany.</hi> But I perſwade my ſelf there is no one can authorize fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Hypocriſie, and falſe Oathes, when we ſtand ſo near the Throne of God; before whom we go to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            <p>And though <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould grant things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which I believe it do's not, is it credible he would confide and rely more upon the Pope, who calls <hi>Bad, Good,</hi> and juſtifies ſo prophane an hypocriſie, than on God who aſſignes the portion of them, who take his name in vain, and of Lyars, and Hypocrites, to be in the lake of fire and Brimſtone.</p>
            <p>Sir, 'Tis then moſt evident the King of <hi>England</hi> lived and dyed a Proteſtant, and by conſequence the allegation is moſt impudent, to ſay, he imbu'd the King his ſonne in the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith.</p>
            <p>The ſecond objection they make to the Religion of this Prince is, that while he was at <hi>Paris,</hi> he frequented not the Sermons. If they could ſay while he was there he made no profeſſion of his Religion, the accuſation were of force and conſiderable, but that no man dares pretend, for 'tis well known the King of <hi>England</hi> had the exerciſes of his Religion, which is ours, in his Palace, and there had the Word of God preached, and the Sacraments adminiſtred, after the manner of <hi>Charenton.</hi> I ſhould certainly have been glad he had been there; and 'tis to be wiſhed thoſe, who were then about him, had brought him thither. So great an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample had brought joy and conſolation to our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168872:12"/>and confuſion to our enemies, who thereby had been depriv'd of their moſt ſpecious pretext to abuſe the Religion of this Prince.</p>
            <p>But there is no honeſt man excuſes not this failing, (permit me ſo to call it, for ſo in effect I judge it, and I believe the edification might have been given to the Church of God, ought to have carried him, beyond all reaſons could be alledged for doing as they did,) if they conſider the many untoward conjunctures that hindered thoſe who attended the Prince from giving him the advice I ſpeak of, which certainly was and the moſt ſure and ſafe.</p>
            <p>It proceeded, Sir, from this, They who were next his perſon after his diſaſters were of different humours. There were many, who though they favoured the Hierarchy ſetled in <hi>England,</hi> under the raigns of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Elizabeth,</hi> and the two Kings who ſucceeded: thought nevertheleſſe that this diſtinction of degrees in Eccleſiaſticall functions was a government ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that it might not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or chang'd into that they call the Presbyterian, judging that this diſtinction of degrees in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call functions is grounded onely <hi>upon a poſitive Law.</hi> Theſe are peaceable people that heartily joyne with forraign Churches, who, though they live not after the ſame diſcipline as they, yet agree in all other doctrine, and I know divers Biſhops whom their books and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute teſtifie to be of this temper: and they who were the more rationall and more knowing, could have been content the King ſhould have been at <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renton.</hi> But there were others near him more paſſionate and rigid for the Hierarchicall Order, who, though
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168872:13"/>they juſtify'd our Religion, as to the Doctrine, could not allow of the Order. This ſort of people are Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to the Presbyterians both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi> Who hold they muſt abſolutely break with the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that conſent to Hierarchical Order, and who are governed by Biſhops, and diſcover in this government ſomething of pomp, which they hold incompatible with the ſimplicity of the Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>The others on the contrary hold the Hierarchicall Order ſo neceſſary to the Church, eſpecially to that of <hi>England,</hi> they can endure no government but that, and have difficulty to communicate in our Churches, though in matter of Doctrine they acknowledge them Orthodox. Now of theſe was the greater number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Prince, who prevailed upon his ſpirit, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd his coming to the preachings at <hi>Charenton,</hi> to which I have been told he had a great inclination.</p>
            <p>But you may obſerve, if you pleaſe, two occaſions whereof theſe Hierarchicall Gentlemen made uſe to divert the intention of the King: the one was, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this horrid revolution of the affairs in <hi>England,</hi> both in Church and State; and that <hi>Cromwell</hi> had inveſted himſelf in the Soveraign Authority, whereof he had deſpoyl'd his Maſter, the Agents of this Uſurper poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed at <hi>Charenton</hi> the Seat of the Embaſſadours of the Kings of <hi>England.</hi> And you will judge that ſince the King our Soveraign admitted them in the function of their Commiſſion near his perſon, 'twas not for the Conſiſtory, or any Proteſtant to diſpute with theſe people concerning the Seat they poſſeſſed at <hi>Charen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton:</hi> Now the party I ſpeak of fayl'd not to take hold on this occaſion, and told the Prince 'twere imprudence
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168872:13"/>to go where he ſhould have the grief to ſee his enemies in the place due to his Embaſſadours. This reaſon touch'd the young King, and he was eaſily perſwaded, &amp; I believe many others were guided by the ſame reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But howſoever, it appears, the reaſon he came not to <hi>Charenton</hi> was not any averſion to the Doctrine preach'd there, but becauſe he could not reſolve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt an object ſo provoking and horrid, and which he judged ſo injurious to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>The other occaſion theſe Hierarchical Gent, made uſe of to divert the Kings inclination from his deſigne of giving teſtimony to our Churches of his ſpiritual communion with us, was that the Paſtours of the Church at <hi>Paris,</hi> who aſſembled at <hi>Charenton,</hi> went not to viſit him; whereupon they ſayl'd not to intimate to this Prince, that this was an evident proof of the averſion of thoſe Churches, both to him and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, ſince thoſe of <hi>Paris,</hi> who make the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part, gave no teſtimony of any ſhare in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. 'Tis true Sir, the Pariſians did ſo, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly carryed themſelves in this affair, quite after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner than the other Churches of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom would have done. I am nevertheleſs far from condemning them, they are perſons that fear God, and which honour the King, and all thoſe that bear the ſame character with the King of <hi>England,</hi> but they are both wiſe and prudent, and know there are eyes upon them, and muſt therefore live with circumſpect on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they had doubtleſs good reaſons that made them think it beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o forbear this duty: Other Churches would have thought to have as ſtrong grounds, to have done in this buſineſs quite otherwiſe than they did at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:168872:14"/>Nevertheleſs I am well aſſur'd that amongſt their reaſons there was neither neglect nor indifferency, nor any hardneſs of heart to partake in his diſtaſter, much leſs any inclination for his enemies, whoſe way with our other Churches they ever deteſted as out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and tyrannical. But to come back to our Subject, you may well perceive, if the King of <hi>England</hi> were not at the Church of <hi>Charenton,</hi> 'twas not that he diſclaimed our communion, nor any diſlike of the Doctrine taught there, but becauſe there were thoſe had incens'd him againſt the Governours of that Church.</p>
            <p>The third reaſon ſcarce deſerves to be ſpoken of, they object, who was ſeen with the Jeſuits at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and at <hi>Veſpers</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> and it may be at other places alſo, and therefore a Roman-Catholick. Once his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſaid he was ſeen at <hi>Maſs,</hi> but that they had not the impudence to ſpeak again: If that were true, there were more colour for the conſequence, but yet no neceſſity neither; he might for curioſity be there to ſee the diverſe myſterious Ceremonies of the Maſſe, and hear the Muſick uſ'd at certain ſolemnities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is ſo much talke. I have known many ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that have been preſent without bending knee, and far enough from approving of it, and would have taken it for a very great injury to have been concluded Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, becauſe they were at Maſſe: but they find more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour than the King of <hi>Engl.</hi> for againſt him they have nothing but that he was at the Jeſuits houſe at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> &amp; to have heard the Muſick at <hi>Veſpers,</hi> yet nevertheleſſe they infer he is a Papiſt. As much as to ſay, that which paſſes for indifferent with other men is a qualifyed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168872:14"/>crime in the Prince. For all this, I do not approve the frequenting places of ſuch devotions: For to omit the viſit of the Jeſuites houſe at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> one of the moſt ſump uous ſtructures of <hi>Europe,</hi> which in effect was but an innocent curioſity, and without the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evill: I much blame thoſe that aſſiſt at <hi>Veſpers,</hi> for they are defil'd with Superſtition, and there they ſing hymns in honour of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which I hold is to reſt upon the Border of the Couch of the ſtrange woman, and to lead himſelfe into temptation. I do not certainly know if the King of <hi>England</hi> were there, but if 'twere ſo; I cannot juſtifie the action. The Prince had done more like a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian if he had not been there at all, and he ought not at all to apply his eyes and eares to ſuch Gaude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Ornaments and Muſick as they honour their Images with, leaſt he ſhould apply his heart, which I well know he Religiouſly reſerves for God. But again, far be it from me to conclude cruelly with his Enemies that he is a Papiſt, becauſe he was at <hi>Veſpers,</hi> and I ſuppoſe you will judge it as unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as I.</p>
            <p>Laſtly they object that the whole world believes him to be a Roman Catholick, and that the Jeſuites promiſe themſelves to be in <hi>London</hi> in the ſame credit, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as they are now in <hi>Flanders,</hi> the Apogie of their domination. I am acquainted with one Father <hi>Talbot</hi> a Jeſuit, that not long ſince, made bonfires in his heart, for the great proſperities he preſag'd (for he is an Aſtrologer) the re-eſtabliſhment of the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould bring to the Roman Catholick Church: But is there any thing more frivolous then to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168872:15"/>ſquare ones opinion and belief by the diſcourſe of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? that pleaſe themſelves with theſe <hi>Idea's,</hi> and make their deſires paſſe for Propheſies, and receive whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Jeſuites affirm and profeſſe to believe, for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere verities. Every one knows the tongue is not of the ſame uſe with them as with other men, &amp; that they keep it not to declare what they think, but to manage &amp; cloak their deſignes, who often ayme at the marke they ſeem to turn their back to. And in effect, Sir, I infer this in my judgment as a demonſtration, becauſe the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits ſay the King of <hi>England</hi> is a Roman Catholick, therefore he is none. For did they believe him ſuch, they would without doubt paſſionately wiſh the rains of the ſtate might be put into his hands, that they might reap, what they ſuppoſe they have ſowen in this agreeable government, and would be cautious of doing or ſaying any thing might obſtruct his re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment: Now the world knows there is nothing can ſo much deprave the affections of the better part of the Engliſh, nor nothing ſo capable to ruine their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of re inthrowning him, as the opinion they give them that he is a Papiſt, which nevertheleſſe the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites do. If the Kings re-eſtabliſhment were to be wrought by a forraine ſtrength of neighbour-Princes, to make an invaſion on his dominions, and become Maſter by force, the Jeſuites diſcourſe might paſſe for a reall rejoycing, for the advantage they might hope ſhould come to their Religion, and their Society in particular. But ſince they know 'tis the People, who of themſelves muſt call him back, if they had ſo great a deſire the buſineſſe ſhould ſucceed, they would be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168872:15"/>cautious how they broach'd any thing might pervert the affection of the people into an averſion againſt their Prince.</p>
            <p>Let us conclude, Sir, this Prince is no ſuch perſon as the Jeſuites report him. That his reeſtabliſhment is not a thing they hope, but fear as a thunderbolt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know if he be once reſtored, he will rectify thoſe diſorders they have fomented, which puſh on their deſignes, and help them to fiſh in troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as they have done hitherto, and that 'twill arrive what the wiſe man obſerves, <hi>that a King that ſitteth in the throne of judgment ſeattereth away all evil with his eyes,</hi> and by conſequence their ways, and all they ſhall endeavour to introduce in his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And to ſet a period to this long diſcourſe, as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the King of <hi>England</hi> is no Roman Catholick, becauſe the Jeſuits feare his re-eſtabliſhment, being to their deſign, what ever countenance they put on; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude likewiſe with me, that 'tis an irrefutable argument his is a reall Proteſtant, ſince all the Miniſters of the Proteſtant Religion in all parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> who are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ignorant in the practice of equivocations, and ſpeak as they think, pray for his re-eſtabliſhment with ſo much inſtance, becauſe they look upon it as an act of ſoveraign Juſtice, and a bud of infinite future bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, like the olive branch brought by the Dove, as a token the deluge was paſſed, and God no longer angry with his people. I profeſſe, Sir. I am one of theſe, not for any conſideration of temporall proſperity may redound to the Church of God, for God courts us not with any ſuch hope, our great reward being with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168872:16"/>him in heaven and were it to be hoped for on earth, I am now become like <hi>Bazillag</hi> the <hi>Gileadite,</hi> I am to old to taſte it. I beſeech God to continue in me ſtill the delight to taſte <hi>How good the Lord is to me</hi> and the conſolation of the portion he hath beſtowed upon me. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Continue to love him that is</hi> YOURS &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
